Okay, so here I have a massive list of
first names. Um,
and they're all stored in an array. So
it says first names equals. There's the
opening square brace. You got a lot of
commas. There's a closing square brace.
And so this is a very very very large
list. Um, and let's say I want to print
out every name in the list. So we could
definitely start. So we'll say
console.log log
um first names at the zero position and
that'll print out Peter
and then I could hold option shift down
and copy this and then say let's go
print out Tony who's in the first
position. So we'll say 0 1
2 3 4 5 6. You can see this is getting
tedious and long and I'm also copying
code and you don't usually want to copy
code. What it would be nice to do is if
I could just have just one line of code
that changed um because really the only
thing changing here is this number and
then I could print out the list of
names.
Well, we do have that code and it is
called a for loop. So let's use a for
loop to print out this list of names.
So, we're going to say four. With our
for loop, we have to tell it where we
want to start. Well, since the array
starts at zero, then we should probably
start at zero. So, I'm going to say let
counter equals 0 semicolon.
Then, we want to run for the array's
length. So, let's say the array just had
three names in it. We would want our
number to be 0, 1, and two. Um, and that
would print out all three names because
Peter's in the zero position, Tony's in
the one position, and Steve is in the
two position.
Well, how many names do we have in the
list? I don't know about you, but I
don't really want to count that. And I
could do math and realize it goes from
line 12 to line 45, but I also don't
really want to do that. And sometimes
our arrays are built um where you can't
see what's in the array. It's built
based on things that have been entered
in from a prompt. or maybe you pulled
this array and you got it from another
computer. Um, you may not know how many
items are in the array, but there is a
handy dandy function or attribute of an
array that you can use. And so we can
say first names dolength
and that tells us exactly how long our
array is. So if there are 20 items in
this array, first names comes out to 20.
Well, now let's go back and look at
this. So if Peter's in the zero
position, Tony's in the one position,
and Steve is in the three position. If
our array has 20 items in it,
then this would be in position number
19, not number 20. Because an array of
three has this in position two, not
number three. So we would want our
counter to start at zero and go almost
up to the length of the name. Because if
we did 20, then we're looking for
something that's not in our array
anymore. If we do 19, then we're in our
array. So, we want to take whatever the
length is and do one less than that. So,
the easiest way to write this is we'd
say run our loop while the counter is
less than the first names.length because
as soon as the h counter gets to the
length, then we don't want to run our
loop anymore. Remember, for loops are
preconditioned loops. So, it's going to
check this condition before it tries to
run the loop. Now, we started at zero
and we want to go up to a certain
number. So, in order to go up, we do
have to increment. So, we're going to
say counter plus+. Then, we're going to
put some curly braces here. And then
we're going to console.log
first names and then what position are
we trying to log? Well, the first time
we go through, we want to log zero. The
second time we go through, we want to
log one. Now, if only there were a
variable for that. And there is. We just
made it. It's this counter variable. So,
if I say counter
and I put a semicolon.
I'm going to delete that and I'm going
to save this. And then I'm going to
close this and I'm going to click go
live. And you can see it printed out all
the names. But that's kind of boring. I
want you to like watch it happen. So,
here on the terminal, I'm going to hit
clear. I'm going to type clear with two
parentheses and a semicolon. That clears
the terminal. Now I'm going to come to
our sources tab and I'm going to put a
break point right here on line 47 and
I'm going to reload the screen. All
right, so we've paused.
Um, if we hover over first names, you
can see it is an array um with 31 names
inside of it. So it turns out my count
was off. I actually didn't count it. I
just threw out a number, but there are
31 names in here. All right. So if we go
to first names at the zero position,
then when counter is zero, first names
at the zero position will be Peter. So
we're going to start our counter. So
we'll hit next. Our counter is now zero.
We'll hit next.
Counter was less than first names.length
because the length is 32. So 0 is less
than 32. So this loop is going to start.
We hit next and we should have just
logged whatever name was in the zero
position. If we go to the console, sure
enough, there's Peter. Well, now let's
hit next. Um, our counter is now one.
One is less than 32. So, we're going to
hit next and we're going to go to first
names in the one position. So, if we go
to first names, we find one. It's the
word Tony. If we hit next, it should
have logged it. If we come to our
console, it's now logged Tony. And this
will continue. And I'm actually going to
remove the break point and hit play. And
it continues until we've done all 32
with the last name of Norin. And now
we've successfully logged every name
inside of our loop.